so this is a Boomer Joe suitor it's the
same Sangeeta nakiya and 12 in the
darkness Anita number 25 so outs savety
then in the evening
the venerable boobie Joe having emerged
from seclusion approached the venerable
sariputta having approached to exchange
greetings together with the venerable
Tsar Peter having exchanged polite
greetings of friendliness the venerable
Bhoomi just said this to venerable
sariputta friend Sarah Goethe there are
some ascetics
and Brahmins with a doctrine of action
who declare that pleasure and pain is
made by oneself and friend sariputta
there are some ascetics and brahmins
with a doctrine of action who declared
that pleasure and pain is made by
something else something apart from
myself so that's what I yeah it's
usually I've seen it two of the main
translations and it's normally pleasure
and pain is babe made by oneself or
pleasure and pain is made by others but
I wonder if it perhaps it'd be more
accurate Paris sankirtan para no sorry
Pat Peron curtain made by para is not
other people but just anything other
than me yeah
well that's that's more comprehensive
yeah anything other than me include
other people but also includes other
things there are not necessary
people yeah but can still be the reason
for me being pushed into action so like
yeah so the things around you the well
to degree the environment yeah deal the
accidents random elements say you've got
so but the point there there needs to be
highlighted is whether the action is
done as in initiated by you or initiated
by other things apart from you if you're
not free from you Givens
you're responsible for your action yeah
yeah and that's why the this is I'm
sorry so perilous things that are not in
your control you are responsible for
yeah I think that will come up again in
a bit later because that's something
that seems to get overlooked and it
translates okay so so you've got
pleasure and pain is made by oneself
pleasure and pain or the summer settles
and Brahmins who who declare that
pleasure and pains may pair something
else there are some ascetic and brahmins
who the doctor action who declared that
pleasure and pain is made by oneself and
made by something else when Sarah puta
there is a some ascetics around in the
doctor erection who declare the pleasure
and pain is not payment made by oneself
not made by something else
arisen without a cause here friend Sarah
Goethe the Buddha's one who says was
he's one who declares what describing in
what way with we be speakers and what
was said by the Buddha so that we could
not be accused of describing the butter
falsely but in accordance with the
Dhamma and they're reasonable verbal
attack could give grounds for criticism
friend it was said by the Buddha the
pleasure and pain had dependently arisen
because of what because of contact
well you've used the word pressure sure
speaking thus what would be a speaker of
what was said by the put her the one
could not be accused of describing the
butter falsely but in accordance with
the Dhamma and no reasonable verbal
attack could go Brown for criticism in
the case friend of those ascetics and
Brahmins and doctrine of action who
declared that pleasure and pains made by
oneself even that is with the support of
pressure hmm in the case of friend of
those assessing food almonds with
reduction of actually declared pleasure
paint paint by something else made by
oneself and made by something else it's
not they by oneself and not yeah
means they view secondary yeah presence
as a representative of what's first
they say the action is because of this
but they fail to see the day around in
the conclusion because they're already
acting out of the pressure they're
trying to explain trying to explain the
pressure which is 37 in the Flies that
look this is how things are
although it's a result of the pressure
my explanation the pressure is the
reason for pressure pretty much and
that's that's in its nature every wrong
view when its secondary that's why the
only way to deal with the wrong view see
the dependent simultaneous presence of
do things or but it's on father because
you can't explain it or rather you can
explain it but then it's imparted
somebody cannot see directly if he falls
on the level of explanation means it's
not seen directly you're explaining it
that's what everybody so father starts
with the principle with this this is not
after this this comes to be with the
presence of this this is present so with
the presence of pressure acting out of
being pressured is present and if your
action out of being pressured is the
explanation of how the pressure came to
be it's going to be great
because if you were truly unaffected by
the pressure which is a position of
being able to understand it and all that
out of it you wouldn't be pressure in
the first place you wouldn't be acting
out of it and then you would be
describing that and you can see that
even like on a practical basis like even
even intentions in a way our form over
pressure they found they were
inseparable you can't even have
intention to do something by Bobby
speech remind if there is no single
taneous presence of some form of
pressure
so even if your intentions are good if
you still acting out of pressure you're
still acting out of ignorance
that's when no more of good action will
result in freedom from ignorance our
hunt is free from good and bad that's
what the only way to start dealing with
the pressure is to start taking
responsibility for your intentions and
of course actions and then take
responsibility for intentions you'll get
to see that you're actually acting out
of pressure and that's what's wrong in
itself so that so so taking
responsibility for one's actions but
recognizing that that is that's all
simultaneously with with the pressure
depression which is not always so you're
not by taking responsibility for your
intentions then they simultaneously the
pressure and which is how you basically
end up allowing the pressure to manifest
by acting out of it you get to see that
you're your responsibility that's where
the line is
it's your intentions in your actions
you're not responsible for the pressure
being there are you responsible for
being pressured and that's a different
thing that's something too you induce
and maintained to acting under pressure
in other words you give the pressure the
power over you to pressure you and
that's what the Buddha said that it's
it's because the monks go and take what
one belongs tomorrow and not to them
Maura does with him but he won't so you
let him in he can't come in unless you
open the door and pull him by the hand
come in or go and take his bait but not
knowing that that's what the line is
then you will be trying to deny the
pressure or get rid of the pressure
because of that pressure so then your
practice becomes practice of denying
there isn't phenomena because you're
affected by the same where is it from
in the first place and that's the
practice of frustration
or go the other way off don't take
responsibility for the pressure because
it's there on its own and then avoid
responsibility for your intentions and
actions that come out of it because
they're there on their own as well but
they're not that's why I need to find
the middle way as in where the line is
where your responsibilities and then not
abandon it that's what the good would
say whenever there is a like an
unwholesome thought would arise in his
mind he would not welcome it no delight
in it not entertain it no doubt of it
and get rid of it basically by not
feeding it to stay longer he will say he
would prevent it from arising in the
first place no even even the Buddha had
to murder the thoughts of Mara coming to
him suddenly for the first few years and
then eventually Mara gave up because he
does there's absolutely no entry but for
as long as there is a possibility of
entry can't keep trying to get in as in
there will be a pressure manifested to
an extent but whether you pressured by
it or not that's a completely different
thing so equating pressure with being
pressured then autumn means basically
acting automatically out of it so you
see you don't see the possibility of
that being pressured but acting out
exactly yeah and that's where you like
either overshoot or undershoot yeah you
can't see the middle ground okay
you don't says in this case friend of
those aesthetics and Brahmas with
adoption of action who declared pleasure
and pain is made by oneself that they
will feel without pressure that is not
possible in the case friends of those
citizen realms we declare pleasure and
pain paipai something else by both I
neither that they will feel without
pressure that is not possible
the venerable Island I heard that the
available services conversation with the
venerable vu major then the venerable
Islander approached the Buddha having
approached to pay respects the Buddha he
sat down at one side sitting down at one
side Ben Hollander told the Buddha about
the entire conversation between Sarah
Putin Buju
good good under answering rightly one
would answer like this
Sarah pewter and that it was said by me
that pleasure and pain are dependently
arisen because of arts because of
pressure speaking last one would be a
speaker upset by me no reasonable would
attack looking for criticism so then you
can ask their sequences pressure
presence of pressure dependent arising
presence of pressure means presence of
pleasure pain but again you're either
puto Jinnah or an area that results in
allergy there is nothing there is no
third option for a human being to be so
you're either with the grain of
ignorance or you're against the grain of
ignorance in other words that is your
responsibility in that pressure not for
the presence of the pressure but for
ignoring the pressure
so for puto Jinnah pressure is the the
simultaneously present cause for feeling
pain and feeling pleasure because he's
ignorant of the pressure so again he's
doing is on the level of his own
ignorance of the pressure not on the
level of that which pressure him that's
just a bait
and you have no say over debate because
that's what matters domain is and that's
what people don't understand when it
comes to potato butter you can
understand it theoretically you're
either with it or against it you ride
the with the grain or against the gap
between you either don't understand it
or you understand it you can't have an
accurate representation or in theory and
still be able to journal because if you
understand it you're a sort of man if
you understand that pleasure and pay are
depending the reason upon the pressure
that's being ignored it's been not
understood you understand it by seeing
it as such and for as long as people
don't see that that's the only those are
the only possible situations you can
either be affected by it or not they
will then use but it's about and all
this as a form of explanation as oxy
pleasure pain arise because of contact
and contact is this mechanical presence
of the eye region no it's not a chef or
a kind of technique yeah because you
don't need to be ignorant to have your
eyes looking don't you so I don't has
eyes has sights doesn't it but if truly
that's like based on some sort of
mechanical setup of petits or pada means
the protein ignorance who then approved
all the senses they wouldn't be there
but it isn't so the pressure is the
cause for pleasure and pain when
ignorance is the cause for the pressure
whereas the other way
absence of ignorance means absence of
you being pressured you wouldn't bring
pressure means you will feel anything on
account of the pressure good or bad
Pleasant or not pleasant
you'll be beyond the feeling yeah so you
can't be understanding the pressure
correctly while you're being pressured
by it
yeah or you cannot be certainly
conveying the pressure correctly while
you're pacified and that's exactly what
it says it'll be in that suit er
whatever statement they make it's
because they're pressured and that's why
this statement is wrong so you can only
understand it when you aren't being
pressured yes and you won't be pressured
but when you understand it yeah
and again I mean how many times people
would say yeah knowledge has arisen
understanding as a reason I'm free from
basically pressure and pain and any
suffered based on the understanding not
based on a theoretical explanation it
pleases my view
these are more disorder yeah there's
this thick this important bit which I
don't think is talked about enough
because I think people just don't
understand it so they just ignore it
[Music]
I'll just go forward to that so he says
for Amanda when there is body on account
of bodily intention pleasure and pain
arise internally or an unknown when
there is speech on account of verbal
intention pleasure and pain horizons
only oh I don't know when there is mind
on account of mental intention pleasure
and pain arise internally and with the
support of ignorance Ananda either he
himself intends that bodily intention
because of which pleasure and pain
arises internally or Ananda things other
than him intend that bodily intention
because of which pleasure and pain is
arises internally so what does that say
ready whether its intended by by you or
by anything else it's because you're
pressured in the first place and the
thing that the usual translations of
this seem to be saying is that pick
another point you said earlier the usual
translation is either one in in terms of
bodily intention for oneself or one's
own initiative or other people instigate
or other people courage you to to to
intend that bodily internship show up in
both cases you are doing the yeah it
does hand in that's the point it's me or
anything else apart from me yeah either
way it's done because of the ignorance
of the pressure right either way I'm
responsible for it I've done this
because of this you've done that because
you're responsible for what you chose to
do what if even if the other thing sort
of did it for you exactly you were
responsible for being affected by the
other thing that resulted in this action
yeah because that'sthat's exactly what
it says what it done by by himself or by
anything about himself
it's whether his ignorance in regard to
it yes
as we just said five minutes ago if
there is no units in regard to pressure
you won't be pressured if you're not
pressured no action will be routed in in
depression internally or externally and
your way to arrive at it is to take
responsibility for both and all so
either one self
I either he himself in terms that
thought intention because of which
passion pain wasn't certainly or things
other than him intend that bodily
intention because of which pleasure and
pain arises internally like things that
ordinary ordinarily you would think well
if it's not me something else then it's
not my responsibility under either with
awareness he intends that bodily
interaction because of which pleasure
and pain arises in certainly or and
without awareness he intends that Bob
continue well if I wasn't aware of it
then it's not my responsibility
exactly yeah that's what people think
yeah but that's the whole point so
whether it's done internally or
externally it's done on the basis of the
pressure yeah and that's what matters
whether it's done internally with
awareness or with other witness but it's
not externally with awareness so what is
that we both with on tables any possible
permutation of doing it is secondary to
the reason why he's doing it and the
reason is the pressure to Gina
you can just say pressure but the
problem is who produces they will say
our case so this pressure that arisen on
account of whatever physical things
that's why these acts happen no the
pressure there is there isn't a kind of
physical things there's not
automatically mean you need to be
emotionally erection fine that's your
ignorance of that pressure that doesn't
matter why how to what extent to what
permutation actions are done if it's
rooted in you feeling on account of
being pressured that's the problem
that's respond that's but that's where
the issue is and three or four minutes
so then it repeats and that's what we
keep saying you know the other talks as
well the difference between the
management of suffering as it doing
things on account of it in order to
prevent it and do and the difference
between that and the difference between
not being affected by it in the first
place whereby you know but no Duty no
requirement you're free the beginning
the middle and in the end and that's
when you remove the ignorance in regard
to the persistent pressure
so then repeats oh and under either he
himself in terms of making them variable
and mental intention hmm or things other
than him in terms or either with
awareness therefore mental or without awareness he
therefore mental or without awareness he
intends that mental attention because of
which passion pains well it also says
that fundamentally to to Gina's
intentions cannot be his own either yeah in other
cannot be his own either yeah in other
words Katrina cannot own even his own
will structurally speaking that's what
possibility of our own ship is possible
its manifesto that's where it can become
like free from any appropriation but for
as long as there is ignorance evening
after the pressure that makes him feel
that will be the reason for his action
and yeah daddy newness is gratuitous
because intentions would be operating on
their own as they do in another hunt but
as the Buddha said all the rituals even
as is beginningless although it's a
parasite it shouldn't be there
it's beginningless as such that's what
once you remove it you cannot come back
cuz he was never there to begin with in
the same sense not knowing that he can
never be there that's why it was there
because the knowledge of not knowing
that ignorance cannot penetrate the
intention in aggregates evil makes you
ignorant of the aggregates Tetsu is also
do Padang is not the father idiots but
it's not found anywhere apart from it in
the rates in regard to the Father I get
super large their desired last in regard
to five minutes open on is their removal
of those in you open up you cannot
reintroduce it in
so the only the only way that the doujin
that will be able to overcome actions
that come out of intentions caused by
him or everything else apart from him is
to start taking responsibility for how
he feels and how he feels is how he's
pressured so knowing how he's pressured
is how much he's even at all the
pressure so not what you choose
basically so exactly its own method of
choice it's not about it's not a matter
of choice is a choice is only the second
area to you being pressure which is why
Aaron still has a choice if choice for
the true reason for for the ignorance
and the pressure it will disappear in an
element but he doesn't so the choice
sure can maintain your state of
ignorance as in more ignoring will
result in you ignorant choices choices
of sensuality ill-will distraction sure
but even in that sense it's secondary
that's why the sense restraint is
necessary as a basis for practice but
it's not directly related to them it
doesn't automatically result in aren't
you but there is no ownership without a
sense restraint so there is no I don't
you without restraining your choice but
you can't become a not by choice
it's by everything which that which
basically didn't
so Souter finishes with so it's talks
about these
various ways in which intentions are
made because of which pleasure and pain
arises internally and this is Ana de in
these things pigments is involved hmm
but the remains of us fading away and
cessation of this very ignorance there
isn't the body because of which our
pleasure and pain arises internally
there isn't speech because of which that
there isn't the mind because of which
that pleasure and pain arises internally
that field isn't there that ground isn't
that domain isn't there cause because of
which that pleasure and pain arises
internally isn't that there is no action
out of plant being pressured when you're
not pressured anymore
how can you act out of pressure there is
no pressure even if you go through the
motion of those actions that's still not
action are the domain of acting under
pressure has ceased irreversibly ceased
that's why are done can still act and do
things but not out of being contacted in
the first place so for puja spoon of you
who can only act out of pressure there
is no action in another hand but going
through the motions of those which used
to be pressured actions that's where I
can move or talk and think cool